CURRICULUM VITAE

Daniel Joseph Gómez Santos

MSc Graduate Student of Biological Sciences and Structural Biology
California State University, East Bay, Hayward, CA, USA
Stanford Cancer Institute, Stanford, CA, USA
Stanford University School of Medicine, Palo Alto, CA, USA

and

Founding Executive Director of Science and Technology at Gomera Health & GomeBio San Francisco, CA, USA

and

Virtual Associate Fellow of Microbiology and Immunology
College of Medicine, Microbiology Control, Drexel University, Philadelphia, PA, USA

Research Interests and Pursuits

I am a graduate student working in the lab of Principal Investigator Kacper Rogala at the Stanford Cancer Institute, where I focus on making fundamental discoveries in Biomedical Innovations through Molecular Medicine. Specifically, my research is centered on organelle biogenesis, including lysosomes and mitochondria, in response to mitochondrial stress. By mechanistically providing insights into nutrient-sensing, nutrient-trafficking, and metabolism-specific tumor suppression pathways, I aim to validate our targets through accurate profiling of supercomplexes using CryoEM structures and nanobody discovery. Ultimately, I hope to inspire medicinal chemists with novel small molecules and design drugs that can prevent various types of cancers.

In addition to my research in cancer science, I also work as a structural biologist and translate my discoveries to the broader cancer research community. Challenges include discovering molecules and designing drugs for cancer neuroscience.

Education & Research Experiences

Current:

M.S. Structural Biology

2022/8-present, California State University, East Bay Stanford Cancer Institute Stanford University School of Medicine Department of Structural Biology Non-Degree Graduate Student

College of Science, School of Life Sciences **Department of Biochemistry and Biophysics**

(Professor: Victor Hsu, PhD)

Bioengineering

Biological cryogenic electron microscopy and tomography.

2023/4-2023/12, Stanford University **Schools of Engineering & Medicine Department of Bioengineering**

(Professor: Wah Chiu, PhD)

Getting started in Cryo-EM

Certificate Program

2023/3-present, California Institute of Technology (Caltech) **Department of Biology and Bioengineering**

(Professor: Grant Jensen, PhD)

Virtual Associate Fellow

2022/6-present, Drexel University **College of Medicine (DUCOM)** Departments of Microbiology and Immunology, **Neurobiology and Anatomy**

(Advisor: Pooja Jain, PhD)

Near Future:

Physical Chemistry

Non-Degree Graduate Student

2023/8–2023/12, **Oregon State University College of Science Department of Chemistry**

Mammalian Molecular Biology and Genomics

Non-Degree Graduate Student

Past:

RapiData 2023

Data Collection and Structure Solving Macromolecular X-Ray Diffraction Measurement

2023/8–2023/12, University of Florida **College of Medicine Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology**

2023/3-2023/4, SLAC National Accelerator Laboratory **Stanford Synchrotron Radiation Lightsource (SSRL)** Structure Molecular Biology (SMB) program U.S. Department of Energy (DOE) Office of Science **Stanford University**

B.S. Biology:

Cell and Molecular Biology

2020/8–2022/5, San Francisco State University College of Science & Engineering **Department of Biology**

> (Advisors: Nicole Salazar Velmeshev, PhD; Michael Goldman, PhD; Scott Roy, PhD)

Research Assistant

2020/1-2020/3, University of Florida College of Veterinary Medicine (UFCVM), **Department of Physiological Sciences**

(Advisors: Chris Vulpe, MD, PhD; Rola Zeidan, PhD)

R&D Coordinator

2015/12-2016/3, hmbldt/dosist

Gomez, Daniel April 29, 2023

Research Assistant

2014/1–2014/6, UCSD School of Medicine VA San Diego Health Care, Department of Anesthesia, Division of Neuroanesthesia

(Advisors: Hemal Petal, PhD; Jan Schilling, MD; Brian Head, PhD)

Graduate Coursework

Neurosciences, Neurovirology

2012/8–2013/6, John A. Burns School of Medicine (JABSOM) University of Hawaii at Manoa Department of Tropical Medicine, Medical Microbiology, and Pharmacology (DTMMMP)

(Professors: Martin Rayner, PhD; Bruce Shiramizu, MD; Vivek Nerurkar, PhD; Linda Chang, MD)

Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine (JHUSOM)

Department of Neurology and Neurosurgery

Division of Neuroimmunology and Neurological Infections

(Professors: Amanda Brown, PhD, Avindra Nath, MD)

Research Assistant

2012/8–2013/7, **JABSOM, DTMMMP**

3

(Advisors: Bruce Shiramizu, MD; Vivek Nerurkar, PhD)

Molecular Cell Biology

2010/8–2013/6, University of Hawaii at Manoa Department of Microbiology (Advisor: Paul Patek, PhD)

Positions & Employment

2023-	MSc Student, Department of Structural Biology, Stanford University School of
	Medicine, Stanford Cancer Insitute
2023-	Founder, Structural Molecular Biologist, Structure Universe LLC
2023-	Director of Multiomics, Biomedical Research Engineering-Scientist (ML Scientist/
	AI Engineer), Gomera Health
2023-	Head of Neuroinformatics and Clinical Biomarkers Program, GomeBio
2023-	VP of STEM Programs, Myplaceisahappy1 (MPH1)
2023	Expert Consultant, Coleman Research
2023-	Chairman, President, Gome Writings Inc, ("Gome-Writer")
2023-	CEO, Director, Gomera Health Inc. ("Gomera")
2022-	Founder/Chief Executive Officer, Gome Bio LLC ("GomeBio")
2022-	Founding Board Member, Myplaceisahappy1 (MPH1)
2022	Teaching Associate, Department of Biological Sciences, College of Science,
	California State University, East Bay
2022-	Graduate Student Researcher, Department of Biology, CSUEB
2022-	Visiting scientist"user", SLAC National Laboratory

-	
2022-	Research Associate, Department of Microbiology & Immunology, Neurobiology
	and Anatomy, Drexel University College of Medicine (DUCOM)
2022	Lab Assistant II/Production Supervisor, Roche Diagnostics (RTD)
2022	Person of Interest, Stanford-SLAC Cryo-EM Center (S ² C ²)
2021-22	Formulations Operator II, TAPP Robotics, Thermo Fisher Scientific
2021	Staff Research Assistant, Department of Bioengineering and Therapeutic Sciences,
	University of California, San Francisco (UCSF)
2020-21	Research Assistant, Department of Biology, SFSU
2020	Research Assistant, Department of Physiological Sciences, Toxicology, University
	of Florida College of Veterinary Medicine (UFCVM)
2019	Manufacturing Associate I, Custom Primers, Thermo Fisher Scientific
2018	Client Relationship Manager, Software Developer, PoshProfiles (BAWF)
2015-16	R&D Coordinator, hmbldt/dosist
2015	Assistant General Manager, Amoura International
2014	Research Assistant, Department of Anesthesia, Division of Neuroanesthesia,
	UCSD School of Medicine, VA Hospital
2013	Research Associate, DTMMMP, JABSOM, UHM
2012-13	Biology Assistant, DTMMMP, JABSOM, UHM
2011	Teaching Assistant, Department of Chemistry, UHM
	·

Honors & Awards

2022	Faculty Member, Graduate, Department of Biological Sciences, CSUEB
2020	DiVERGE Awardee, Scripps Research Institute
2013	Grant Awardee, Undergraduate Research Opportunity Program (UROP), UHM

Poster Presentations

Co-infection and Human Cancer: Viral Oncogenesis leads to Host-Pathogen-Tumor-Body Interactions, 2023/4, Berkeley, CA. 22nd Annual UC Berkeley Microbiology Student Symposium.

Co-infection and cancer: Viral oncogenesis in humans result in liver, blood, and brain cancer by host-pathogen interactions, 2022/12, Honolulu, HI. 12th Annual American Association for Cancer Research (AACR) - Japanese Cancer Associate (JCA) Joint Conference.

Oral Presentations

Immunoreagent Design and Production in Vaccine Development: Rational Design, High-Throughput Production, and Integration of Structure and Computation, 2023/06, Virtual meeting. Vaccines Research 2023 eConference (Vaccines-eCon2023). The Research Catalyst.

Unraveling the Structural Dynamics of HPgV-1 NS5B Using Computational Methods. Grand Slam Graduate Research Presentation Competition, Cal State East Bay Grand Slam 2023, CSU East Bay.

Pioneering organelle structural biology: Golgi apparatus dysfunction and cascades of fatal pathways in cancer, 2023/03, Virtual meeting. Cells 2023 Conference. MDPI. sciforum.

Landscape of Myeloid and Astrocyte phenotypes in acute MS lesions + Future Technological Directions, 2023/01, Virtual presentation. Drexel University College of Medicine, Department of Microbiology and Immunology, Neurobiology and Anatomy. (Jain Lab)

Structure-based discovery of RdRp NS5B in HPgV (GBV-C) by macromolecular crystallography (MX), 2022/12, In-person & Virtual presentation. Cell and Molecular Biology Seminar: CSU East Bay.

Retron Library Recombineering (RLR): Going beyond CRISPR, 2022/11, In-person & Virtual presentation. Cell and Molecular Biology Journal Club: CSU East Bay.

PathAR 6th Annual Cal State East Bay Hack Day, Hack the Outbreak, CSU East Bay, *Hackathon*, and oral presentation

Ribozyme mechanisms and Clinical Gene Therapy, 2022/10, Virtual meeting. Chemistry 2022, Global Virtual Summit on Chemistry & Pharmaceutical Chemistry.

A Human Retrovirus in Neuro-Oncology, Interventional Conductome Studies, and Theranostics in Nuclear Medicine, 2022/10, Virtual meeting. 5th International Webinar on Cancer Research and Oncology.

Cancers: PCNSL outcome in EBV+/HIV Confection and HTLV connection in HIV/AIDS patients, 2022/10, Virtual presentation. Drexel University College of Medicine, Department of Microbiology and Immunology, Neurobiology and Anatomy. (Jain Lab)

HTLV-1: From neuroimaging to neurosurgery and biomarkers of neuroinflammation and neurodegeneration in HAM/TSP progression, 2022/10, Virtual seminar. Cell and Molecular Biology Seminar: CSU East Bay.

Hackathon "Hack the Outbreak": PathAR, 2022/10, In-person & Virtual presentation. CSU East Bay.

An intasome story: Structural basis of host protein hijacking in human T-cell leukemia virus integration, 2022/09, Virtual seminar. Cell and Molecular Biology Seminar: CSU East Bay.

Deltaretrovirus: HTLV, 2022/09, Virtual seminar. Cell and Molecular Biology Seminar: CSU East Bay.

Data Driven Discovery of Computational Oncology and Modern Molecular Biology, 2022/5, Virtual seminar. Data Science Research and Career Seminar: CSU Northridge.

Editorial Team

Academic Editor

• Cancers: Neuro-oncology and neurotrauma

Editorial Board Member

Bioengineering

Journal Referee

- Biology
- Cancers
- Cells
- Healthcare
- International Journal of Molecular Sciences (IJMS)
- Pharmaceuticals
- Viruses

First/Co-first Author Publications

+: Co-first Author. *: Co-Corresponding Author

D.J. Gómez*. Untangling the Microscopic World of Organelles, Cells, Tissues, and Organs: A Focus on the Dysfunctional Golgi Apparatus in Disease Research. <u>Biology and Life Sciences</u> Forum. 2023

D.J. Gomez-Santos, G. Sandel, R. Kulkarni, J. Joseph, S. Maher, P. Jain*. **Epitope-Based Vaccines and Immunotherapy for Infection-Related Cancers in People Living with HIV: Current Status, Challenges, and Future Directions.** *Frontiers in Cellular and Infection Microbiology.* 2023 (In preparation)

D.J. Gomez-Santos, B. Lucke-Wold*. Neuroendovascular embolization procedure optimization for aneurysm subarachnoid hemorrhage healing by drug eluting biomedical devices, robotics, and artificial intelligence. *Bioengineering*. 2023 (In preparation)

Gomez, Daniel April 29, 2023

- D. Gomez*. Unraveling the Structural Dynamics of Human Pegivirus-1 RNA-Dependent RNA Polymerase Using Computational Methods. *ResearchGate* 2022. DOI: 10.13140/RG.2.2.11957.35041
- D. Gomez*, Pioneering Organelle Structural Biology: Golgi apparatus dysfunction in Parkinson's Disease, Neurodevelopmental Disorders, and Cancer. *Preprints*, 2022, 2022100383. doi: 10.20944/preprints202210.0383.v2.

T.H. Mulherkar⁺, **D.J. Gomez**⁺, G. Sandel, P. Jain^{*}, **Co-infection and cancer: Host-Pathogen Interaction between Dendritic Cells and HIV-1, HTLV-1, and Other Oncogenic Viruses.**2022 Sep 14;14(9):2037. doi: 10.3390/v14092037. PMID: 36146843; PMCID: PMC9503663.

Teaching, Training, Mentoring Experience

University Service (University of Florida)

Spring 2023- UF MHPMP Mentor, Minority Health Professional Mentorship Program (MHPMP), Pre-Health Club

Instructional Activities (CSUEB)

Fall 2022 BIOL230 (Clinical Microbiology), (4 unit course) - 2 sections

Fall 2022 BIOL270 (Human Anatomy & Physiology I), (4 unit course) - 1 section

Instructional Activities (University of Hawaii)

Spring 2011 CHEM161L (General Chemistry I Laboratory), (1 unit course) - 2 sections

University Service (University of Hawaii)

Tutor, Chemistry, Biology, Organic Chemistry (Emporium)

University Service (Modesto Junior College)

Teacher, English Language; Thailand, Laos (Study Abroad)

Interns

2022 Chier Hu, PhD, Computer Engineer Intern at Gome Bio LLC

Undergraduate Student Mentees

2022 Courtney-Jane Lopez, CNA, CSUEB, Pre-Nursing

Daniil Mudrov, CSUEB, Cell and Molecular Biology (RA, MEDGENOME > Genentech)

Yongtao Guan, CSUEB, Ohlone College, Pre-med (MCB)

2022 Arielle Vue, CSUEB, Pre-Nursing

Volunteering

Professional Service

2023-	Editorial Board Member, Bioengineering MDPI
2023-	Academic Editor, Cancers MDPI, Special Issue: Neuro-oncology and neurotrauma
2022-	Founding Board Member, VP of STEM Programs, Myplaceisahappy1 (MPH1)
2022-	Volunteer Reviewer (VR), MDPI
2012	Volunteer, Physician Shadowing, Dr. Thomas Slavin, Pediatrics and Clinical Genetics,
	Medical Genetics section, City of Hope

Community Service

2022	Volunteer, St. Michael's Church
2022	Lighting Designer, Fountain Church
2014	Market Research, Berkeley Human Society
2014	Community Wellness Advocate, American Cancer Society
2014	Anesthesiology Technician, VA San Diego Health Care, VA Medical-Center

University Service (University of Florida)

2019-20 Scientific Ambassador, Microbiology

University Service (University of Hawaii)

2011 Tutor, Chemistry, Biology, Organic Chemistry (Learning Emporium)

Certifications & Licensure

2023	SSRL RapiData 2023: Data Collection and Structure Solving: A Practical Course in Macromolecular X-Ray Diffraction Measurement SLAC SSRL
2023 (<i>pending</i>)	Deep Learning with PyTorch for Medical Image Analysis
2023 (pending)	Reinforcement Learning beginner to master - AI in Python
2023 (pending)	Modern Artificial Intelligence Masterclass: Build 6 Projects
2023 (pending)	Deep Learning: Convolutional Neural Networks (CNN) in Python
2023 (<i>pending</i>)	A deep understanding of deep learning (DL)
2023	The Complete Quantum Computing Course
2023	Scientific Computing with NumPy - Python Data Science
2023	Writing High Performance Python
2023	Database Design
2023	Beginning C++ Programming - From Beginner to Beyond
2023	Complete linear algebra: theory and implementation in code

2023	Reviewer Certificate (MDPI Journal - Biology, Cancers, Pharmaceuticals, IJMS,
	Viruses, Cells, Healthcare)
2022	Cyber Security for Lab Users, SLAC National Accelerator Laboratory
2019	IRB Training
2019	Life Sciences Responsible Conduct of Research Course (RCR)
2018	Medical School Pathology – Certificate of Achievement
2018	Modern Golang Programming, Packt Publishing
2018	Learning Path: Go: Building Cloud Native Go Applications, Packt
2018	Mastering Go Programming, Packt Publishing
2017	DNA Research with Biopython
2017	Data Science and Machine Learning Bootcamp with R
2017	Google's Go (golang) Programming Language
2017	Python for Data Science and Machine Learning
2016	Intro to SQL for Data Science Course - DataCamp

Professional Trainings & Workshops

2023	Vaccine Technology Workshop. World Vaccine Congress, Washington, DC.
2023	HIV Workshop. World Vaccine Congress, Washington, DC.
2023	Biodefense: Vaccines & Antibodies. World Vaccine Congress, Washington, DC.
2023	RapiData 2023 at SSRL: Data Collection and Structure Solving: A Practical
	Course in Macromolecular X-Ray Diffraction Measurement, SLAC
	National Accelerator Laboratory, Stanford Synchrotron Radiation
	Lightsource (SSRL), SMB, U.S. Department of Energy, Office of Science
2022	5th Annual Cal State East Back Hack Day (Hack the Outbreak): Created an
	AR prototype of a epitope based measles vaccine to MV-H:SLAM fusion
2022	The Upside of Downturns Summit, Startup Grind Silicon Valley, SF Bay
	Area
2022	IEDB Virtual User Workshop La Jolla Institute for Immunology
	Immune Epitope Database and Analysis Resource, Funded by the National Institute of
	Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)
2022	SSRL/LCLS Users' Meeting Stanford-SLAC National Accelerator Laboratory
2022	Stanford-SLAC Cryo-EM Center (S ² C ²), SCSC – Training on Electron Microscopes and
	Computers (Under the direction of Wah Chiu), cryo-FIB/SEM milling
2022	UW-Madison, Department of Biochemistry, 42 nd Steenbock Symposium, Opening Doors
	to Cryo-EM, Titan Krios G3 and G4 workshop, Cryo-electron tomography, SerialEM

Technical Strength

Languages: English (Native), Spanish (Communicative), French (Novice), Arabic (Novice), Hebrew (Beginner)

Skills: Strong background in biology, biochemistry, and/or biophysics. Knowledge of protein structure and function, as well as other biomolecules such as nucleic acids and carbohydrates. Familiarity with experimental techniques used in structural biology, such as x-ray crystallography, NMR spectroscopy, electron microscopy, hybrid structural mass spectrometry (HDX-MS, etc), and computational modeling. Ability to perform protein expression, purification, and characterization, including chromatography, electrophoresis, and spectrophotometry. Competence in computer programming and data analysis, as well as experience with data visualization and statistical analysis, Familiarity with laboratory safety protocols and good laboratory practices, including handling of hazardous materials and biological samples. Strong problem-solving and critical thinking skills, including the ability to troubleshoot experimental issues and design creative solutions. Excellent communication and collaboration skills, including the ability to work effectively in a team environment and to present research findings to diverse audiences.

Digital Proficiency: Benchling, Photoshop, Illustrator, Biorender, Linux, GitHub, Shell scripting, Shiny

Programming Languages: Go , R , Python , C++ , HTML, MATLAB, Bash.







Bioinformatic Tools and Databases: BioPerl, Biopython, IGV, APE, BLAST, Bedtool, Bioconductor, RNAseq, scRNAseq, Seurat, 10X Genomics pipelines, Proteomics, The Cancer Genome Atlas (TCGA), nucamino, COSMIC, Roche Cancer Genome Database (RCGDB)